Southern Tenant Farmers Union Records on Microfilm 5204 mf
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- September 1959 to December 1959, Undated 1959, Miscellaneous Union Business 1959, and January 1960 to May 1960. (Reel 43)
  - April and May, 1960, 7 (Reel 43)
    The union's crisis remained at a standstill until May 6, when George Meany telephoned Mitchell to inform him of the AFL-CIO Executive Council's decision that the NAWU must return its charter; see Mitchell's memorandum on the conversation (May 6). Negotiations began almost at once with the Amalgamated Meat Cutters Union to formulate a merger agreement; see Mitchell's detailed memorandum to Leon Schachter on arranging the merger (May 19), his letter to Galarza on the telephone conversation between Meany and AMC Secretary-Treasurer Patrick Gorman (May 25), and the resolution on the merger submitted to the NAWU membership in a referendum (May 26). There are numerous reports from Galarza on the situation in California, a set of AWOC bulletins on its activities (April 21, 25, 26), and a press release from the Di Giorgio Fruit Corporation announcing a $2 million libel suit against the NAWU, the AWOC, and the UPWA for showing the film "Poverty in the Valley of Plenty" which the NAWU had agreed to remove from circulation in 1950 (May 18).
- June 1960 to December 1960, Undated 1960, Miscellaneous Union Business 1960, and January 1961 to April 1961. (Reel 44)
  - June to August, 1960, 1 (Reel 44)
    On August 2, 1960, the NAWU ended its existence as an AFL-CIO International Union and became a department of the Amalgamated Meat Cutters Union. Important items relating to the merger include: a long letter from Mitchell to Harry R. Poole (June 3); the minutes and report of the NAWU Executive Board (June 26); a letter from Mitchell to all NAWU locals announcing the final tally of the membership vote on the merger (July 18); Mitchell's memorandum to the AMC on an organizing campaign among agricultural and allied workers (July 19); and the final merger agreement (Aug 2). On the continuing dispute with the AWOC and UPWA, see Mitchell's letters to Galarza and Fay Bennett (June 1, 2), the rather bitter exchange between UPWA President Ralph Helstein and Mitchell (June 6, 10, 17), the correspondence from AWOC Director Norman Smith (June 2; July 9; Aug 3), and Gorman to Mitchell on his conversation with Meany on securing eventual AMC jurisdiction over the field workers organized by AWOC (July 21). There is a copy of "Workers in Our Fields", an illustrated booklet published by the NAWU on its 25th anniversary (n.d. [June])
  - September and October, 1960, 2 (Reel 44)
    The papers include the minutes of the first meeting of the Executive Board of Agricultural and Allied Workers Union, Local 300 (Sept 24). On Mitchell's activities, including his initial organizing trip to Louisiana as an AMC representative, see his letters to AMC Executive Vice-President Harry R. Poole (Sept 11, 19; Oct 25). Mitchell began to formulate plans for a low-key educational campaign for civil rights in the rural South; see his memorandum to NSF on this subject (Oct 10), as well as his letters to NSF Chairman Frank P. Graham and Board Member Cyrus I. Gordon (Oct 12, 31). There are letters to Dr Graham written in support of Mitchell's proposal from Daniel H. Pollitt (Oct. 14 ) and Gardner Jackson (Oct 20)
  - November and December, 1960, 3 (Reel 44)
    The apparent failure of AWOC in California and the influence of UPWA on the AWOC continued to trouble Mitchell; see his exchange with Patrick Gorman (Nov 1, 16), Galarza's letters on the California situation (Dec 12, 24), a memorandum from Franz Daniel to George Meany replying to Mitchell's charges that AWOC was UPWA-dominated (Dec 9), and Mitchell to Gorman, commenting on the memorandum at length (Dec 29). On Mitchell's growing involvement in the civil rights campaign in the South, the papers include his report on a staff meeting on the AFL-CIO Civil Rights Department (Nov 14), a statement by Harry Fleishman, Director of the National Labor Service of the American Jewish Committee on "Equality and the Unions" (Nov 14), and Mitchell to AFL-CIO Civil Rights Director Boris Shiskin on discrimination against blacks in Memphis unions (Nov 28). On the plans for a new AMC organizing drive among agricultural workers, see especially the exchange between Mitchell and both AMC President Thomas J. Lloyd and Patrick Gorman (Dec 5, 8, 9)
  - No Date, 1960, 4 (Reel 44)
    Statement of H.L. Mitchell on "Regulations on Referral of Workers in Agricultural Labor Disputes"; Statement of the California Citizens Committee For Agricultural Labor on "Legal Aspects of Legislative Discrimination Against Agricultural Labor"
  - Miscellaneous Union Business, 1960, 5 (Reel 44)
    Folder 1589 -- Weekly organizer's reports of H.L. Mitchell [Note: expense sheets attached to the reports were not filmed]. Folders 1590, 1590a, and 1590b -- Routine correspondence. Folders 1592a to 1592c -- Not Filmed
  - January and February, 1961, 6 (Reel 44)
    Mitchell became deeply involved in a civil rights crisis in Fayette and Haywood Counties, Tennessee, where black sharecroppers who had attempted to register for voting had received threats of eviction from their homes. On this subject, see Mitchell's detailed memorandum (Jan 17), the minutes of a meeting held at Le Moyne College in Memphis to deal with the problem (Jan 21), and a report by "Operation Freedom" (Feb 2). Legal papers relating to a suit filed against the White Citizens Council in Jackson, Mississippi appear in the undated section for January. On the situation in California, the papers include two letters from Gorman to Mitchell (Jan 9, 25) as well as one from Gorman to Norman Smith, protesting against excessive UPWA influence in AWOC (Jan 26). There is a long letter from Mitchell to Gorman, proposing that the AMC set up an "organized migration" program to provide southern farm workers with jobs in the North (Jan 19).
  - March and April, 1961, 7 (Reel 44)
    Mitchell moved from Memphis to Lake Charles, Louisiana, at the beginning of March to begin a campaign to organize rice mill workers. On the campaign, see his detailed proposal to the AMC (March 4), his letters to Leon Schachter (March 27; April 28), and the letters from leadership toward the campaign (April 13, 19). There is a letter from C.O. Cabe on his work organizing Louisiana dairy plants (April 3), and a letter and set of documents from the American Bakery and Confectionary Workers Union, Local 370, on the anti-union tactics of the Huval Baking Co. of Lafayette, Louisiana (April 10). The papers include a letter from Mitchell to NSF Chairman Frank P. Graham requesting a grant for a survey of Louisiana sugar cane workers (March 6), and two letters from Galarza on the situation in California and on his dispute with AMC (March 22, April 4)
- May 1961 to December 1961, Undated 1961, and Miscellaneous Union Business 1961. (Reel 45)
  - May to July, 1961, 1 (Reel 45)
    For a running account of the progress of the organizing campaign among Louisiana rice mill workers, see Mitchell's letters to Schachter (May 22) and to AMC Secretary-Treasurer Patrick Gorman (May 29; June 9, 26; July 30). The papers also include a set of flyers handed out to the rice workers (May 22, n.d. [May]) and a letter from the NLRB Regional Office on the eligibility of seasonal rice workers in NLRB elections (June 29). Gorman and Mitchell kept up an exchange of correspondence throughout these three months on the collapse of the AWOC in California and on the attempts of the Teamsters Union to organize California agricultural workers. Finally, there is a memorandum from Mitchell to Gorman on the background of the National Farm Organization and on the difficulties of organizing small farmers (March 9)
  - August to October, 1961, 2 (Reel 45)
    Mitchell's letters to Patrick Gorman (Aug 16, 23; Sept 2; Oct 31) and to AMC Executive Vice-President Harry Poole (Oct 2, 17, 26) again provide a running account of the rice mill organizing campaign. The NSF Board of Directors decided to approve Mitchell's request for a survey of sugar cane workers; see the letter from NSF Executive Secretary Fay Bennett announcing the Board's action (Aug. 1), and the correspondence from Frank Lapeyrolerie, a former NAWU organizer assigned to carry out the project. There is a long memorandum by Mitchell on his meeting with Tom S. Bavin, General Secretary of the International Federation of Plantation, Agricultural and Allied Workers on a suggested dues structure and program for organizing agricultural workers (Sept 14). The papers also include a report by Mitchell to the AFL-CIO Southern Civil Rights Advisory Committee on his work in this area during the previous year (Sept 29), and a lengthy press release from the Senate Sub-Committee on Migratory Labor on its activities (Sept 26)
  - November and December, 1961, 3 (Reel 45)
    The campaign to organize Louisiana rice mill workers at Lake Charles and at Crowley continued through the end of the year; see Mitchell's reports to Harry F. Poole (Nov 9) and Patrick Gorman (Nov 27; Dec 11, 14), the correspondence with organizer Gene Collins at Crowley, and the returns of a survey of "seasonal" employees of the Louisiana State Rice Milling Co., filed at the end of December. Information on the survey of Louisiana sugar cane workers appears in the exchange between Mitchell and LSU economist Ray Marshall (Nov 3; Dec 5, 11) and in the reports of Frank Lapeyrolerie
  - No Date, 1961, 4 (Reel 45)
    Draft of an NSF "White Paper" on the "Present Situation and Suggested Program for Southern Sharecroppers"; a "short report" on job discrimination against black workers in Memphis, Tennessee; materials relating to the rice mill workers organizing campaign, including flyers, lists, etc
  - Miscellaneous Union Business, 1961, 5 (Reel 45)
    Folder 1621a -- Survey of Louisiana sugar cane workers -- nine completed returns and several working papers. Folder 1621b -- Organizer's reports of H.L. Mitchell. Folder 1622 -- Local 300 organizer's reports, exclusive of H.L. Mitchell. Folders 1623 to 1629 -- Not Filmed.
- January 1962 to September 1962. (Reel 46)
  - January to March, 1962, 1 (Reel 46)
    For a running account of Mitchell's activities during this winter, during which he lost an NLRB election at the Louisiana State Rice Milling Co. and turned to other organizing prospects, see his weekly reports from Gene V. Collins, Willie Berry, and other members of the Local 300 staff. On legal matters, see Mitchell's correspondence with Local 300 lawyer James Youngdahl. An especially interesting legal case arose with the Sweetlake Land and Oil Co., Inc., a corporation farm which claimed that its employees were all agricultural workers and thus excluded from NLRB coverage. On this dispute, see Mitchell to a lawyer Daniel H. Pollitt (March 14), the briefs filed by both the union and the corporation with the NLRB (March 23), and a detailed report on the Sweetlake Co. (n.d. [March])
  - April to June, 1962, 2 (Reel 46)
    Local 300 had three different cases before the NLRB during the Spring of this year. The first case involved a Borden Co. dairy plant in Lake Charles, Louisiana, where the local management began a strong counterattack against the union with the aid of the New Orleans law firm of Kullman and Lang; the papers include the transcript of the NLRB representation hearing (April 11), the brief filed by the Borden Co. with the NLRB (April 25), and a set of unfair labor practice charges filed by the union against the company (April 26 to May 3). the second case involved the union's dispute with the Sweetlake Land and Oil Co.; see the additional briefs filed by both the company and the union (April 19, 23). The third dispute was with the Louisiana Rice Growers, Inc., at Crowley; see the union's Motion to Close Record (May 2), the company's reply (May 11), and the briefs filed by both sides with the NLRB (June 15, 16). Mitchell's weekly reports to Patrick Gorman again provide a running account of the activities of Local 300
  - July to September, 1962, 3 (Reel 46)
    For the remainder of the year, Local 300 became mired in litigation before the NLRB. Most of the litigation concerned the unsuccessful attempt to organize the Borden Co. dairy plant in Lake Charles, Louisiana; copies of the various legal papers filed by the company, the union, and the NLRB itself appear throughout this three month period. There is also a generous sample of the anti-union flyers which the company sent its employees shortly before the election (Sept 12 to 21). On the other cases before the Board, see the NLRB decision in the Sweetlake Land and Oil Co. case, in which the Board held that employees of the firm were not agricultural workers and hence came under NLRB jurisdiction (Aug. 15), and the union's Complaint on the Conduct of An Election in the Rice By-Products Co. case (Aug. 31). For an overview of the litigation, see Mitchell's exchange of correspondence with lawyer James Youngdahl (Aug. 29; Sept 3, 6, 10). There is also a four-page report by Mitchell summarizing his first year of work in Louisiana (Aug 15).
- October 1962 to December 1962, Undated 1962, Miscellaneous Union Business 1962, and January 1963 to June 1963. (Reel 47)
  - October to December, 1962, 1 (Reel 47)
    The papers include the key legal documents in five cases placed before the NLRB by Local 300. In the Borden Co. case, see the Complaint on the Conduct of An Election filed by the union (Oct. 1), the Brief of the NLRB General Counsel on the union's charge of unfair labor practices against the company (Nov 23), and the NLRB Intermediate Report on the case (Dec 6). There is a copy of the NLRB decision to hold an election in the Louisiana Rice Growers, Inc. case (Oct 5), as well as the union's challenge of the election (Oct 26). In the Sweetlake Land and Oil Co. case, see the complaints of unfair labor practices filed by the union (Nov 1, 26; Dec 18). Local 300 attempted to organize a Lake Charles plant of the Stedman Co., a wholesale fruit and vegetable firm; the papers include the briefs filed by both union and company (Oct 26, 30) and the NLRB Decision and Direction of Election in the case (Nov 19). Perhaps most interesting of all was Mitchell's effort to obtain NLRB action against the New Orleans law firm of Kullman and Lang, which had represented the Borden Co. in its fight with Local 300. See the Motion to Disqualify Attorney for the Employer which Mitchell filed against Kullman and Lang in the Stedman Co. case (Oct 27), as well as his formal charge in an unfair labor practice against the law firm in the Borden case, enclosing a seven-page affidavit on Kullman and Lang's participation in the dispute (Nov 13)
  - No Date, 1962, 2 (Reel 47)
    Organizer's report (no name or date); "Report on the Sugar Cane Plantation Worker Survey in Louisiana"; survey of unorganized workers in the food, agricultural, and allied industries in Lake Charles, Louisiana; file of correspondence between the Louisiana Rice Growers, Inc. and the NLRB, 1954-1956; survey of regular and seasonal employees of the Louisiana State Rice Milling Co. at Lake Charles, Louisiana
  - Miscellaneous Union Business, 1962, 3 (Reel 47)
    Folder 1567 -- not filmed
  - January to March, 1963, 4 (Reel 47)
    Local 300 attempted to organize a group of egghouse workers at the corporation farm of the Sweetlake Land and Oil Co. near Lake Charles, but the union drive stalled when the employer insisted that his employees were agricultural workers and did not come under the NLRB jurisdiction. On the Sweetlake case, see Mitchell's memorandum on the NLRB hearings (Jan 22), the various briefs filed in the case (Feb 4), the NLRB decision (Feb 11), and the tally of ballots in the NLRB election (March 4). Mitchell began a project to convince the government and the NSF to set up a program for training unskilled sugar cane workers in the operation of modern farm equipment; information on this subject appears in Mitchell's correspondence with NSF Executive Secretary Fay Bennet, and in Mitchell's exchange with Seymour L. Wolfbein, Director of the Office of Manpower, Automation and Training of the US Department of Labor (Jan 16; Feb 11). The campaign of Local 300 to organize the menhaden fishing industry might best be followed in Mitchell's weekly reports to Patrick Gorman
  - April to June, 1963, 5 (Reel 47)
    Legal papers relating to the unfair labor practice charge with Local 300 filed against the Sweetlake Land and Oil Co. appear on April 4 and 5 and on May 7 and 28. Mitchell's correspondence with the NSF on a proposed training program for sugar cane workers continues through June; see also his letter to NSF Executive Secretary Fay Bennett on the completion of a survey of sugar workers which the NSF financed (May 8). The main activity of Local 300 this Spring was the organizing drive among menhaden fisherman. Mitchell detailed the progress of the campaign in his letters to Patrick Gorman; see also the exchange between lawyer James Youngdahl and Mitchell on strategy before the NLRB in a dispute with the Louisiana Menhaden Co. (May 27, 28).
- July 1963 to December 1963, Undated 1963, and Miscellaneous Union Business 1963. (Reel 48)
  - July to September, 1963, 1 (Reel 48)
    Nearly all of the activity of Local 300 was devoted to the organizing drive in the menhaden fishing industry during this summer. There are legal papers relating to disputes between the union and the Louisiana Menhaden Co. (July 29; Sept 23) and the Fish Meal and Oil Co. and Quinn Menhaden Fisheries, Inc. (Sept. 11, 27). See also the tally of ballots in the various NLRB elections held on the fishing boats (Aug 20; Sept 21). The union filed an unfair labor practice charges against the Louisiana State Rice Milling Co. (Sept 17); in addition, see Mitchell's memorandum on the dispute (n.d. [Sept]). There is an exchange between Mitchell and the Department of Agriculture on setting a minimum wage for sugar cane workers (Aug 20, Sept 5)
  - October to December, 1963, 2 (Reel 48)
    The organizing drive in the menhaden fishing industry continued with a series of NLRB elections and legal wrangles. Ballot tallies appear on October 18, 22 and 23. There are memoranda by Mitchell on the Louisiana Menhaden Co. case (Oct 10) and on "NLRB Elections on Menhaden Fishing Botes in Louisiana" (Oct 25). The union filed unfair labor charges against several fishing companies; see the affidavits collected from fishermen to document the charges (Nov 14, 21) and Mitchell's letters to lawyer Spiro T. Agnew on settling the cases (Dec. 13, 18, 27). The papers include a number of legal papers relating to the Louisiana State Rice Milling Co. case (Oct 17, 19, 24; Nov 6); see also Mitchell's letters to the NLRB General Counsel on his complaints against the company (Nov 15; Dec 12, 31). Finally, there is a report by Mitchell on the farm machine training project for Louisiana sugar cane workers which Local 300 was closely involved in (n.d. [Oct.])
  - No Date, 1963, 3 (Reel 48)
    Office Diary of H.L. Mitchell; letters from Eugene Cox; Report by Mitchell on "Carrier Boats of the Menhaden Fishing Industry"; two proposals for an on-the-job training program in farm machinery for Louisiana sugar workers; proposed contracts with menhaden fishing companies; Xerox copies of documents relating to the unionization of the menhaden fishing industry in 1963 [Note: several of these items are dated and may be duplicated in the regular chronological series]; lists of employees of the Louisiana State Rice Milling Co.; flyers sent to rice workers
  - Miscellaneous Union Business, 1963, 4 (Reel 48)
    Folder 1704e -- Not filmed.
- January 1964 to September 1964. (Reel 49)
  - January to March, 1964, 1 (Reel 49)
    For information on the organizing drive among menhaden fishermen and the resulting battles before the NLRB, see Mitchell's weekly letters to AMC Secretary-Treasurer Patrick Gorman. There are a number of affidavits of fishermen (Jan 15, 30), as well as an illustrated pamphlet by Mitchell entitled "Pogy Boat Men" (March 1). The fishermen campaign began to take on an increasingly strong civil rights dimension, which appears explicitly in Mitchell's exchange of correspondence with the Congress of Racial Equality (March 1, 11, 13, 27). There is also a bulletin from NSF on its new contract with the Department of Labor to set up a demonstration manpower training program among southern agricultural workers (Jan 16)
  - April to June, 1964, 2 (Reel 49)
    Local 300 continued to win a sizable number of NLRB elections on menhaden fishing boats; the official tallies of ballots appear in the papers (May 15; June 12, 20, 27). However, the problem soon became one of signing contracts with owners once the union acquired the status of certified bargaining agent; see Mitchell's memorandum, giving a chronological account of his negotiations to sign contracts (May 27), as well as several contracts which were finally signed (May 29). There is an interesting exchange between lawyer James Youngdahl and Mitchell on the cases currently before the NLRB (April 10, 12) and a letter from Mitchell to various menhaden companies protesting the deductions from workers' pay made to cover the cost of extra crew members (June 10). The papers include Mitchell's statement to the public hearings held in Washington by the National Advisory Committee on Farm Labor and a lengthy report on the hearings published by the Committee (May 18). Information on the sugar worker training program sponsored by Local 300 appears in Mitchell's letter to NSF Executive Secretary Fay Bennett (April 17) and in a report to Mitchell from Frank Lapeyrolerie (June 3)
  - July to September, 1964, 3 (Reel 49)
    Mitchell concentrated his efforts during this summer on obtaining contracts for the boats on which NLRB elections had already been won; see his exchange of correspondence with AMC President T.J. Lloyd on his use of threats of job action to force the companies to sign (Aug. 7, 11; Sept 19) and the contracts themselves (July 18; Aug 4, 14, 18; Sept 23). For further information on the menhaden organizing drive, see especially the reports of organizers Howard Harrity and Willie Berry, Mitchell's report to the Local 300 Executive Board (Sept 13), and his exchanges with James Youngdahl on NLRB cases (July 22, 24; Aug 4, 14, 15). There is a letter from Fay Bennett describing an attack on the NSF by the Mississippi Farm Bureau (Sept 23) and a long letter from Mitchell to Henry Anderson on the accomplishments of the TFU (July 6).
- October 1964 to December 1964, Undated 1964, Miscellaneous Union Business 1964, and January 1965 to April 1965. (Reel 50)
  - October to December, 1964, 1 (Reel 50)
    The main topic in the papers for these months is Mitchell's attempt to obtain better contracts for menhaden fishermen which would be in compliance with the safety standards set under the Jones Act; see especially his letters to AMC Maryland organizer Melvin H. Tyler (Oct. 10) and to lawyer James Youngdahl (Nov 19) and a draft copy of the proposed contract (Nov 23). There is also a memorandum by Mitchell on the status of the contract negotiations (Dec 13). Another important issue was the demand of the fishermen for a separate AMC charter, which Mitchell opposed on the grounds that the resulting local would be all black; see his exchange with organizer Willie Berry (Nov 18, 21) and his letter to Patrick Gorman on this subject (Nov 19). The papers include an interesting letter from Mitchell to Eugene Cox on the problems of the Southern Rural Training Project (Oct 14) and one to Fay Bennett on the future role of NSF in the South (Dec. 21)
  - No Date, 1964, 2 (Reel 50)